Guide to the David I. Wells papers, 1964-1980.
Wells, David I. papers, 1964-1980.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
David I. Wells papers, 1964-1980.
4917
David I. Wells.
19 cubic feet.
Correspondence, subject files, legal briefs and papers, and other material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, subject files, legal briefs and papers, and other material pertaining to Wells' career and interest in legislative representation and redistricting, including the Wells Vs. Rockefeller Supreme Court challenge, anti-gerrymandering legislation, presidential election system reform, and other legal cases concerning districting and reform.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Lecturer and writer on matters of apportionment.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, subject files, legal briefs and papers, and other material pertaining to Wells' career and interest in legislative representation and redistricting, including the Wells Vs. Rockefeller Supreme Court challenge, anti-gerrymandering legislation, presidential election system reform, and other legal cases concerning districting and reform.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wells, David I.
Subjects:
Wells vs. Rockefeller (suit).; Apportionment (Election law).; Legislation.; Legislative bodies.; Presidents--Election.; Representative government and representation.; Gerrymandering.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- D.W. written materials (several folders) (Box 1-2)
- Correspondence to D.W. (Box 3)
- Correspondence by D.W. (Box 3)
- Articles and letters mentioning D.W. (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous D.W. activities and involvements (Box 3)
- Dirksen Amendment ( 1964-1965 ) (efforts to nullify "one person-one vote" ruling) (Box 3)
- Legislative Representation in New York State ("LRNYS") - a booklet by D.W., issued in several editions between 1957 and 1964 (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Wells v. Rockefeller ( 1966-1970 ) - case challenging three successive New York State Congressional Districting redistricting statutes (1961, 1968, 1970) - the first two successfully. Second phase ruling (1969) was by U.S. Supreme Court. (Box 4-6)
- General material on redistricting reform (mostly late 1970s, early 1980s) (Box 6)
- Proposed Danford Amendment (U.S. Senate) ( 1979, 1980 ) (Box 6)
- WMCA case (WMCA v. Lomenzo). Case which, when consolidated with cases from five other states, became the so-called "one person-one vote" Supreme Court ruling of 1964 (3 folders) (Box 7)
- New York State Committee for Fair Representation ("NYSCFR") - 2 folders (successful) (Box 7)
- National Committee for Fair Representation ("NCFR") (Box 7)
- "Black-Republican Redistricting Alliance" (Box 7)
- Race and redistricting, post-1980 (Box 7)
- Voting Rights Act Extension ( 1982 ) (Box 7)
- Schwartz case, 1971-1972 (subsequently combined with Schnider v. Rockefeller) - attacking constitutionalityof New York State legislative redistricting of 1971-1972 (4 folders) (Box 8)
- 1974 N.Y.S. racial redistricting ruling, leading to United Jewish Organizations (UJO) v. Carey (Box 8)
- Proposed federal anti-gerrymandering legislation (Box 9)
- D.W. consultation work (national), initiated through AFL-CIO COPE (post-1970 redistricting) - 2 folders (Box 9)
- Informal Advisory Committee on Redistricting to Democratic National Committee (DNC) (Box 9)
- Articles & commentaries on redistricting (early 1970s ) (2 folders) (Box 9)
- State legislative redistricting (national), 1971-1972 (Box 9)
- Local redistricting (Box 9)
- DW, GT (Gus Tyler) and other's writing on redistricting - early 1970s (Box 9)
- Articles on redistricting, post- 1980 (Box 9)
- Computer redistricting, post- 1980 (Box 9)
- Congressional redistricting (national), 1971-1974 (Box 10)
- Legal briefs on redistricting (most early 1970 s) (Box 10)
- Legal decisions on redistricting (most early 1970 s) (Box 10)
- Presidential election system reform; the Electoral College (Box 11-12)
- Summaries of events & cases, post- 1970 redistricting (Box 12)
- 1992 N.Y.S. congressional redistricting, including D.W. plan submitted to task force (Box 12)
- State-by-state files on redistricting, in alphabetical order, beginning with this box which runs from Alabama through Georgia (Box 13)
  State files contain various materials on redistricting in the state in general, as well as some correspondence and other material on D.W. involvements in the state. Note, for example, Colorado, where League of Women Voters successfully campaigned to get proposal drafted in part by D.W. onto the ballot through initiative process. Proposal passed (1974) and was incorporated into state constitution.
- State-by-state files, continued (Hawaii through Missouri) (Box 14)
  NOTE: Pre-1990 files for twelve states (Idaho through Minnesota, alphabetically) are missing.
- State-by-state files, continued (Montana through New Jersey) (Box 15)
  NOTE: New Jersey files include extensive material on D.W. involvement in N.J. congressional redistricting in early 1970s at initial request of Congressman (and House Judiciary Committee Chairman) Peter Rodino.
- State-by-state files, continued (New Mexico through Oklahoma) (Box 16)
- State-by-state files, continued (Oregon through Vermont) (Box 17)
- State-by-state files, continued (Virginia through Wyoming, plus Canada, France, Japan, etc.) (Box 18)
- Books on various aspects of districting and apportionment - mostly historic ( late 1950s, early 1960s ) (Box 19)